um we've been discussing the nine levels
of
meditation here we
go so the
fourth stage the first fourth level of
meditation is called maintaining the
Mind tightly on the
object your ability to hold the object
has has become quite powerful right
and thus we say that you are now
maintaining the Mind tightly on the
object from this point on from the
opening of the fourth level it's not
possible that you will lose the object
completely all right you won't fully
leave the object and take a about lunch
all right you will you will always have
the object slightly in mind
and this is what differentiates step
four from Step the first three at the
first three you can still lose the
object completely and number four you
won't be losing the
object but there's an equal uh strength
to the dullness and the restlessness
that you feel as you are on the object
all right so dullness and and
restlessness are are attacking you
strongly at this
point so you will have to use the
antidotes for dullness and
restlessness uh level three and level
four are achieved through a strength of
the ability to hold on to the object we
call awareness right
Nar Nar it's a rare word if you see it
up there Nar
somewhere so Nar narba means uh full
grown it refers to people who are grown
up so at this
point he says your ability to hold the
object is grown up you're not like a kid
anymore uh you have a grown up ability
to hold the object Nar Nar or we can say
or we can say the capacity Your Capacity
to hold the object is complete or or
full in his
power so now we're on to the fifth level
of meditation called controlling the
mind and
again the great blessing of this
presentation of 11 levels of meditation
is that you know where you are at any
given day you you know how far you are
along in your own meditation you can say
I've reached level four I've reached
level three if you still if it's still
possible for you to start thinking about
lunch during a meditation session you
haven't gotten to level four
right
okay sorry okay
[Music]
during the fourth stage the previous
stage you were able to draw the mind in
right you drawing the mind in is a
concept in Buddhist uh study of the mind
it happens for example when you fall
asleep when you fall asleep the Mind
withdraws prara right your mind
withdraws from the objects of sense and
gathers into the inside of the mind so
at stage four there's that same
gathering in of the mind it's a prar
withdrawal of the Mind from the outside
room but dud cha means you you go you go
too far you go too far in withdrawing
the Mind from the outer
World which makes it very fertile ground
for subtle dullness right you overdo the
withdrawal of the Mind
come outter objects and that makes you
very susceptible to to subtle
dullness so what state of mind do you
think you would have to crank up at
level
five yeah the Watcher mind Shin okay you
would have to crank up the part of your
mind which is watching the rest of your
mind okay that that has to be cranked up
you no longer have to worry about what
we call awareness or the to hold on to
the object that's fully developed that's
grown up but now because you're on the
object and you're tending to move too
much to the inside too much withdrawal
there's a danger of subtle dullness and
then you have to put Watch Dog M at the
back of your head to watch out for
subtle
dness you have to set CH is a very rare
word those of you who care about the but
CH say CH so these
are these are uh synonyms okay SOA means
uh spy like a military
spy the the great G name is SAA okay I
mean Tibetans always win when people
call him G
SAA or SOA R you know they're like he's
not a spy uh it's
okay that's SAA which is patience uh SOA
means a spy Char is an old word for
soapa all right so you should put the
spy mind spy camera going in the back of
your head this area is under
surveillance all right uh I saw these
signs recently okay uh
sh it's cheaper than buying cameras you
just put the signs up
we we did that in the
D so
you you think about and you do s do you
remember s from the other day what
s you uplift the mind okay you uplift
the Mind by thinking of something cool
all right I think about the last award I
got and I you know like everybody has
their own s something that would make
you kind of perk up all right something
nice that will make your mind per up
what is the He suggests thinking about
how cool it's going to be when you
become a great meditator right if you
need to perk up your mind a little bit
s uh by thinking about how cool it's
going to be when you become a good
meditator
uh there's a distinction
between the the way you remember the how
many nine levels the way you remember
the difference between the nine levels
and in fact it's the question on your
homework is is what's the difference
between this level and the left one you
see just give yourself a self- exam uh
if you know why each level is different
from the one before then you that
defines the levels you see so he says on
level
five uh there's a difference between the
three and four and five because at five
uh you don't get obvious dullness and
and restlessness all right you don't get
obvious forms of which implies that at
the previous two levels you did okay
that's what distinguishes level what are
we on five five from four and three all
right
now level number
six uh at the fifth level you were
perking up the mind and
you over
per okay that remember everything is
going to go too far and then you turn
back right if that's constant and don't
feel bad about it okay you have to make
a correction you apply a correction perk
my mind up think about something good
that's happening in my life and I hope I
have a good job tomorrow and I hope by
then then you go too far and then you
have to bring it back okay it's a
constant correction
process and then there will be a danger
of
you perked up too
much subtle
restlessness okay you over and you will
get subtle
Restless if you get subtle
restlessness uh first before you fix it
you have
to detect it right with the Spy M right
with the spy camera
go good uh then you can stop it by
considering how bad it's going to mess
up your meditation right probably it
will lead to gross restlessness which
means that you'll just get off the
object and you'll drop down below level
number four four okay all right if if
subtle restlessness gets out of hand at
level six there's a danger you could FL
back to third grade all
right got good just thinking about that
is supposed to be enough to bring you
down okay and then you don't have subtle
restlessness anymore all
right what distinguishes number six from
number five is that you no longer have a
problem
of settled dness right okay now you have
a little problem with subtle
restlessness because you overcorrected
for subtle
dumbness
okay the power of the mind which
accomplishes fifth and sixth levels is
the Watch Dog M okay or
okay and at the sixth level we can say
that the power
of your Watchdog mind is consumated it's
the you now possess a a
fully empowered ability to watch the
rest of your mind
okay
D at the seventh
level
your both both your awareness or your
ability to stay on the
object and your watch do mind are are
fully completed right by then by the
seventh level those two abilities the
ability to hang on to the object and the
ability to watch yourself to see whether
you're getting dull or Restless okay
these two positive states of Mind are in
their are already developed to their
fullest
form and therefore it's difficult to get
cha or Goa to it's difficult at this
point to get dullness
or to get restlessness at sudden it's
difficult to get
[Music]
them now you have to make some kind of
subtle efforts more you have to keep
trying to perfect things right the the
power at this point is called effort you
have to make further efforts it's like
you're pretty good at a yoga pose but
you want to perfect it and it almost
takes more energy to perfect a yoga pose
that you're good at than it does to
learn it in the first place
right you have to be in a state of mind
where even a very brief subtle form of
dullness or restlessness is not
acceptable to you okay it's like a
person who got really good at yoga you
know so you can do a
handstand uh but then you decide that
that being shaky in a handstand or
moving in a handstand is unacceptable
you want to be perfect so this is also
applies to your ability to overcome
subtle and gross forms of dullness and
restlessness any kind of any hint of
restlessness any hint of dullness is no
longer acceptable to you
the difference between this and the
previous uh I'm sorry the difference
between this and the previous level is
that you you no longer have any serious
concern that you might fall into subtle
or gross dullness or restlessness okay
that's a m right what's m
it
implies that you might have some less
serious concern right you have no
serious concern that they might come
back even though at this point there's
no major danger of falling into either
subtle restlessness or
dullness nonetheless you still must make
some considerable effort effort to to
prevent the two you're still making
considerable effort to prevent the two
all right at this point
number at the fifth and sixth
levels you can have
some
worries that uh dness and restlessness
are going to attack you all right you
can have some wor
[Music]
but at the seventh level if you just
make a little bit of effort you can stop
them all right with a slight effort you
can stop them by the seventh
level so there will be no major uh
interruptions of the flow of meditation
by this point by by dullness and
restlessness by the seventh level there
are no longer any any serious
[Music]
interruptions uh they
Define everything from the Third
level up to the fifth
level as being uh you are in a state of
meditative
concentration mostly in a state mostly
the majority of time you're in a state
of meditative concentration but you will
be interrupted constantly
by dullness and restlessness okay so you
are in meditation you are in deep
meditation but from the third level
up to the seventh level up through the
seventh level uh it it feels like you're
getting interrupted all the time
right so the the feeling inside the mind
as it is is like
uh I don't
know it's like it's like uh you're
working on your computer but somebody's
interrupting you from time to time all
right like you have a flow of
concentration on your computer
you're writing a a translation okay and
then people from time to time somebody
interrupts you so the feeling inside the
Mind from the third level to the seventh
level is one of being interrupted from
time to time by dullness or
restlessness so now we're up to stage
eight right at level eight
okay after beginning of the
session you exert a little effort to
shut down any subtle dullness or subtle
restlessness right at the beginning of
the session of the meditation session
you have to put forth a little effort to
shut down any any form of dness or or
restlessness and then uh t ring means
for the length of the whole session they
don't com back so it takes some effort
at the beginning to to correct the car
to the middle and then you just let go
the steering wheel and it's it's gone
cruise control all right and and there's
there's no more uh effort needed to stay
there you put up a little bit of effort
forth at the beginning of at level
and then the whole session goes smooth
without any dness or
rest he says you can compare all of the
levels up to here as
being they are there are changes in the
strength of your
enemy there are changes in the strength
of your
enemy so in the first levels the draw is
the en the enemy is strong okay in the
first few levels the enemy is a strong
enemy a we you
know someone to worry about
right then in the middle you feel like
the enemy has been slightly what do you
call
that compromised or
weakened there's another
word not sub D
yet uh they're halfway like they lost
their
tanks there's a military word isn't
they compromised I guess compromised
their forces have been compromised
somewhat Neal neutralized in the middle
in the middle stages of meditation and
then at the end to Z then at the end
they're like you know they threw away
their guns and they have their hands up
and you could still call them enemy but
they don't have any power to hurt you
right
okay the
power of the dullness and the power of
the restlessness have been lost they
can't touch you anymore they they become
there's a word
there's a bad there kind of hard
word impotent yeah they have become
impotent they can't they can't hurt
you so from the eighth level on what
state of mind do you think becomes
unnecessary yeah okay watchfulness is no
longer necessary because watch n's job
was to Ring the Alarm nowadays they have
this alarm on the car if you get too
close to the curve or you're backing up
and there's something within two feet
and an alarm button goes off so that
that that can be shut off it's not going
to happen you won't get close to the
garbage cans uh there there's not going
to be any there's no chance for any uh
Collision to come you you're not going
to fall into subtle dullness or or
subtle uh
restlessness and that's the point at
which they say up what's
that yeah the best meditation is the
best letting go that's the point at
which you can say okay just draw it you
the things off
[Music]
this is called the the level at which
you are you are in the flow and there's
no more interruptions okay so there
there's not a possibility of interrup
like you're just working on your
computer and and there's no possibility
of someone calling you on the phone or
some you know nobody's going to talk to
you you're you're on a flow and there
will no
interruptions the feeling of the
meditation at that point is like ah you
know I'm not going to nobody's going to
be interrupting me for the next half
hour I really like
airplanes I love airplanes they say it's
a 12-hour flight gu I'm like ah you know
because they just bring you orange juice
and you just work and there's not going
to be any phone calls or interruptions
and like that then they started to put
phones in the business class of my boss
[Music]
out the seventh and eighth levels are
said to be achieved through some amount
of effort you do have to put forth some
amount of
effort to cruise at that
point which gives you a clue about the
ninth level which is what
what effortless totally effortless I I
like to say you know you you get you
like what do you call
it you call it when a child is
like yeah you fidget you fidget down on
your cushion you know you do this
chicken I don't know it must be a dance
and then you sit down and you're like
you know in your neck and you get your
and then you go like this right and then
boom when the hands hit the knees you're
in you're you're in your deep meditation
your the hands hit the knees you see
without even having to think uh there
isn't even the effort it takes to think
I'm going to meditate or you let me
collect my thoughts you know or let me
watch my breath or something like that
you don't need any of it your your hands
hit your knees and you're there you're
already there it's a beautiful feeling
right
what's happening
says is that you have got so used to
level eight that it has become automatic
you're on
autopilot okay because of the hours you
spent at level
eight you don't need need the slightest
effort to collect your thoughts or to
calm your breath down or you know try to
reach your object or anything like that
you just your hands touch your knees and
you're
there in the monastery uh we're required
to memorize hundreds and hundreds of
pages of text okay when you go to the
debate ground you can't take a a book I
took a book one night and they laughed
me out of the debate gun you know they
said no no you can't bring a book to
debate you know you have to know the
book by heart and then you can come you
know so then you have to memorize the
book and then there's different ways of
knowing a book by heart right you can
say uh what do we
[Music]
do g g g
g what was that again chway okay not
like that uh they require that you know
it as second
nature what else you want like that it
has to be totally what do you call it
reflexive it has to be a reflex like to
to to pull out a quotation in a debate
has to be reflex no no pausing
so is comparing a person who's reached
level nine to a person who's memorized
the text flawlessly and reflexively it
just they just spout it they don't stop
to think about
it thing in shy J shy J means you just
CL shy sh
sayy just
Glide dny yeah it's like silky but it's
shy okay probably it's a lone word uh
[Music]
this is a single pointed State of Mind
the what's
the
what's what's
the desire what's the
come desire realm okay the lowest realm
there are three Realms of existence we
are in the desire realm which is soall
because people are mostly thinking about
food or sex okay most of people's
efforts in this realm is directed
towards food or sex so it's called the
desire
real uh then there are higher Realms
there are worlds that we don't see where
there are the beings are very happy
temporarily called form realm they're
very beautiful it's like go to the go to
some expensive Resort in Phoenix right
and people are like walking around in
nice clothes and jewelry and all they
have to worry about is you know is the
limo going to be in front when I get out
of the restaurant and that's like a form
realm then there's a formless realm
where you don't even have a body anymore
and you're just hanging out in a
blissful state of mind and these are
temporary paradises okay uh each of
those three
Realms is reached by a different state
of mind
to get to the desire realm you have to
be doing emails most of the day all
right in this life then when you die you
will go to the desire room okay because
your mind will be busy and and that when
you
die in a state of mind where you've had
uh email stuff all day for you know 10
years or something if you suddenly get
hit by a car uh that will throw you into
the desire room
uh if you meditate most of the day or
you meditate a lot or you're in a 3year
retreat you know and you I don't know
your comp compul toilet eats you or
something I don't know okay but anyway
it'll probably happen with somebody
uh then uh then you go to the formal you
see your mind goes to this uh Phoenix
Resort state state of being okay it's
temporary we consider it a
obstacle uh so but but you feel very
happy okay that realm after you die can
only be reached by a person who has
spent most of their time meditating in
this life okay so the number of people
in the world who go to that realm are
there's only a couple okay then formless
realm means they've been in meditation
most of almost all day in deep
meditation and then they if they die
they go to a thing called performance
okay so what the reason I'm mentioning
that is that different levels of
meditation different depths of
meditation are sometimes named by where
you go if you suddenly die doing it
right so desire realm meditation
means a meditation which was not so good
and if you died during it you would be
born in a desire room form real
meditation means uh if you died doing it
you would you would end up in a form
realm in your next life so when I say
form realm meditation does that mean
you're doing it in the form real no it
means you are in such a deep state of
concentration that if you were to die
that week uh you would be reborn in a in
a form so you have to learn that you
have to know that there are four form
realm meditations there are four
formless realm
meditations that why did it come up here
he said level N is
a it's
a it's a desire realm state of mind
which is single pointed right it's a
desire realm state of mind which is
single
pointed to see emptiness directly which
is the purpose of this whole
exercise your mind must already be into
formal meary some say something
something
it's a specific sliver of the
meditational spectrum that you have to
be in to see emptiness directly our
whole exercise of meditating is to get
our mind into that small sliver of the
whole spectrum of
meditation and that in that sliver
you're able to see emptiness directly
okay it happens to be the very very
first brushes of a form real meditation
okay if if you get to the point that you
need to get to to see emptiness directly
and you died suddenly in that moment you
would be born in a form real okay it's
a dumble means the first form real
level so I have a question for you he
just called he said he says Dan D he
just called the ninth level of
meditation a desire realm State of Mind
single pointed but desirable is it
enough to see emptiness so could it be
shamat it's
not okay level nine is not enough okay
level nine is not the state of mind you
need to see an this directly it's not
good
enough okay
the point at which you put your palms on
your knees and you're into deep
meditation immediately with no effort at
all is not good
enough right if you want to be depressed
okay J Jumba means getting
hot okay it's
approximate it's it's approximate shamat
but not real shamata it's like it's like
right up there close to Sham jba means
really really close but not there no
cigar close but no
okay you get to level n through a power
called uh High
familiarity at level eight okay
so by by doing level eight over and over
again you get to level n
[Music]
then he Compares
uh he he's
saying as you pass through the nine
levels you will get sort of a feeling
what's it feel like to pass through the
nine level number one
uh in the first couple stages you feel
like you're just getting to know your
enemy okay you're just getting to know
your enemy you become able to tell
you're having done
this okay uh it's cool right like in the
first part of your meditation career the
only accomplishment you can claim is
that you know when you have
vness okay or you know when you're
Restless that's all and that's a big
progress that's big progress to know
you're distracted is Big progress
because before that you were just
distracted all the time and you had no
idea right so to recognize the enemy is
the feeling of the first part of your
meditation line okay second
part you feel like uh your distractions
are are cutting you some slack
sometimes okay like they are relaxing
from time to time your dullness and your
restlessness are not attacking you
actively all the time like it seems like
they're taking a break once in a while
that's the feeling of the second part of
your meditation life third part
s then in the third in the final stages
of your medit meditation career it feels
as
if the interruptions to your
meditation
have become exhausted okay they're not
just taking a break once in a while
they're
too feeble to bother you anymore if they
just seem to be like they're just like
what do you call it scile or something
your your Don get okay
he's going to wrap
up the nine levels of meditation now
he's going to wrap up the nine levels of
meditation by repeating how each level
differs from the one before it okay I
said before I think I made a mistake I
said how it differs from the previous
two or something like that it's not with
the Tibet said we are going to review
how each level differs from the one
before and that will give you a stronger
memory of of what the levels are and
this is on your homew okay here we
go that what distinguishes level one
from level two is the length of your
fixation on the object how long can you
stay on the object the only difference
between level one and level two well the
main difference is that in level two
your mind is on the object a little bit
longer than at level
one how will you know that you got to
level
two there'll be a little more
continuity okay there'll be a few
minutes of continuity
what differen differentiates the third
level from the second is the length of
your
distractedness the sustain what do you
call it the the sustained the length at
which you are have can have a sustained
distraction becomes what less okay good
yeah you
you you'll know you got the three from
from two if the time that you are
thinking about lunch gets
less but it's still there and it's still
sustained but it's shorter than it was
before what separates level four from
level three is whether or not you are
even capable of losing the object
anymore at four you are
not capable of losing the object
completely at three you are still
capable of losing the object completely
so how do you know that you reach
four yeah you don't lose the object when
you don't lose the object anymore when
it becomes impossible for you to lose
the object during the meditation session
you have reach
form
G what differentiates five from four
is whether or not you can still get
gross forms of dullness right if you can
honestly say I don't get gross forms of
dullness and how did he describe gross
forms of
dullness like you feel like you're going
to fall asleep you feel heavy the mind
and and body feel heavy and you feel
like you could fall asleep if you reach
a stage in your meditations where you
never ever feel like you're going to
fall SLE okay then you have
level five
okay
good what separates five from six is
whether or not uh you have to worry a
lot about getting subtle dullness right
what separates five from six is whether
or not you have to worry about a lot
about getting subtle
this is all just words now okay I'm just
you know telling you words in
January we explore the real thingi you
know we say we'll we'll do like
meditation so we'll say did you lose the
object today did you lose the object in
the last five
minutes you know or are you getting dull
right now and like that we we'll do it
experientially this is I'm planting a
seed I'm planting a crop which I'm going
to reap in January okay I'm just
planting seeds and then I want you here
in January and I then we're going
to bear bear fruits right it's going to
bear fruit okay as Alison
[Music]
say he adds another qualifier to
level six uh you will also get less
subtle restlessness than you got
before what's the difference between
level seven
and six
okay is there any serious possibility
that you will get uh that you will fall
into
subtle dullness or subtle
restlessness
done okay by the way I'm I'm a little
bit dissatisfied with that right I mean
if you look at the difference between 6
and five and seven and six the
difference between his descriptions is
not so clear he's going to come back
later and he's aware of that all right
just so you know he's coming back later
to make some more comments on it because
it's not even for me to teach it it's
uncomfortable I I don't see a big
difference between them
okay the difference between seven and8
is whether or not you have any dullness
or any restlessness at
all the difference between eight and N
is you know
what do you have to make the slightest
effort to to go into deep meditation do
you even have to collect your thoughts
you know do you have to say I'm going to
meditate now like that no you just boom
your in all
right now he cor now he qualifies the
seven the thing about level
seven at the seventh
level uh you're just shutting down
dullness and restlessness
but there's no great need to be overly
concerned during the session you you
shut it down but you don't have to be
very what do you
call Vigilant like that he he calls it
concern you don't have to have any great
worry that they're going to come they
come a little bit and you shut them down
but it's not like you have to think oh
I'm I'm at risk of those happening you
don't feel at risk of them happening
they happen slightly and you shut them
down but you don't have to have a sense
of being at risk for them
okay when you are in a boxing match okay
and the other guy is tuckered out
completely then you can let your guard
down you know like you don't have to be
like cuz a guy who's not tired out yet
he can still throw a lucky punch in
Florida right like there's a thing in
boxing where you have to stay aware of
there's a you just have to constantly
stay aware even if you're a superior
boxer because the other guy could just
get one lucky punch in and knock you out
right but at stage seven he's so tired
out that you you know you don't have to
look for the lucky punch you don't have
to worry that dness or restlessness is
going to is going to be able to stck you
a good one when you're not looking all
right you don't have to be looking out
so carefully got it
okay then you just
uh you just shut you just stop them you
punch them you know if the guy makes
some kind of you know he's totally
exhausted you've got to be and he's like
he goes back for a punch and then you
just F you know like it's no big match
at that point you know if he decides to
try to throw a punch he's going to be
really slow you know and then you just
go you know like that no great need to
be very Vigilant about a powerful punch
being thrown at you by dness or
restlessness all
right uh that would be a good place to
stop and detecting give you a break but
I don't
care this is cool those of you who have
purchased the English translation of the
book which is well done all right uh
we're not trying to make money we're
just uh We've Got It On consignment and
we're selling it to you for what we buy
it I think right so we're not making a
penny on it uh it's good to have the
book okay it's good to take the book
home with you and have it if you get the
book be aware that we just everything
we've done in the whole week is a single
day from P's teaching okay that was day
21 out of 24 all right like he was
moving no they had 12 14 hour sessions
you know and they're brutal especially
if they have the peeee okay
uh so now we're on
day 22 we are starting day 22 of the
record of teaching
by the tutor
of the current Val Lama and my heart
Lama's heart Lama okay here we
go he's you know he started his talks
with
announcements and then somebody hit you
up for some project or some money and
then he quoted Master Chand okay he
quotes Master
chti because in day 22 he's going to
move from what to
what he's going to finish how to
meditate deeply and then he's going to
tell you how to use that meditation how
to apply that meditation what are you
going to use that meditation for okay
this is a famous quotation okay uh a
bird needs two wings okay a bird needs
two Wings shock means uh wides
spreading powerful Wings carpo means
they are white wides spreading Wings you
know like the kind of Angel wraps around
you from the
back
G they are spread
wide and those are he calls them let me
get it straight uh he calls them the
apparent and the
real the apparent and the
real and he doesn't say anything more
about th do do the king of all uh
geese fly ahead of the flock of the
other geese meaning bodis
safas
D he or she flies at the front of the V
right and
d and with the power of their
goodness they travel to the other side
of the vast ocean of the the qualities
of an enlightened being meaning they
gather into themselves all the qualities
of enlightened being they go
from what's that place uh start to the
Venice Beach to
Osaka okay they cross the ocean meaning
they collect all the good the vast good
qualities oflen
people the apparent or the decep
and the real or the ultimate he says as
referring to the wish for enlightenment
it is referring to the wish for
enlightenment
okay uh a univer I wish that all living
creatures in many worlds all worlds
could become enlightened and Escape
their suffering we call the deceptive
form or the apparent form of their wish
for enlightenment right it is still
wrapped up in the deceptive world world
right still on the level of a of the
world around us which is fooling us
right and then there's a higher form of
that mind which is called CH
say uh which they call the ultimate form
of the wish for enlightenment the
ultimate form of the wish for
enlightenment and that
is it's just another word for the direct
perception of emptiness right it's just
another word the ultimate form of the
wish for enlightenment is just another
expression for seeing emptiness directly
right we talked about it the other night
I think right you need both wings uh
just to the most lovely bird you could
imagine but if they had one Wing cut off
they would they they would just flop on
the ground we we had a what it called
last time we went to Sanja there with a
what was that thing a pelican there was
a pelican and apparently he had broken a
wing or something and uh he was flopping
around the beach and the the local
people were going to kill him and then
one of the students in the class he
said one of the students in the class
said I'm going to take care of the
Pelican you know so the whole six day
seven day teaching he took care of the
pelican and the pela bit him countless
times and uh he was running around his
room and he had to clean up these huge
poops from his room and and then uh the
last day he it was cute because the last
day he said well I got to leave I got to
go back to America and he paid some
Mexican person to keep the Pelican and
he handed the Pelican to the Mexican
person and the Pelican flew away I'm the
hand off you flew
away uh so I guess it was just strange
or something but um
to have a single wing you it's no use
for a bird you know he will die he can't
eat he can't do anything right
so if you do good
deeds if you try to help if you try to
save the world without understanding
where the world is coming from you are
like a bird with One
Wing you are as ineffective as a bird
with one you try to save the world
without knowing where the world has
really come from you are like a bird
with
[Music]
one you can also read this uh two wings
as you know we
say there two kinds of collections of
good C okay one which is a collection of
Mer and the collection of wisd
if you want to save the world and if you
have the understanding which will give
you
the the capacity to save the world then
you then you then you become an
enlightened both
[Music]
wings uh
then because he was starting a new day
of his teaching he reviewed the need for
learning formal instruction in these
things uh he reviewed the need to uh
study he reviewed the need to do the
preliminary practices which you will
learn okay this book is one of the best
books ever written on the preliminary
practices how to prepare the mind for
meditation
CH sh he he he he gave a summary of what
he had taught in the previous
days and he brought everybody up on the
outline how far they had gone in the
steps to Enlightenment oh we covered
that we covered that we covered that we
covered
[Music]
that he reviewed the conditions that you
would have to gather together to start
your study of shamata your practice of
sham
J and he said you could call it either
five or six conditions is that
correct he said you can call it either
correct yeah because there's six but
there's five in the first we all right
am I
right say yes you can go
okay you'll have a threee retreat to
work it
out D then he went into the actual
details about how to how to reach sh as
opposed to the conditions you have to
get ready before you sit
down he described to us once again the
five problems and the eight fixes for
de then he described how you get you go
through nine levels
as you go through the process of
applying the eight antidotes to the five
PRS good are we all right
dup means he repeated these subjects for
us he he repeated those instructions for
us so there are you'll get used to this
later okay there are five problems there
are eight antidotes for them there are
nine levels of concentration that you
meditation that you go through
uh and now he's going to talk about he's
just summarizing okay six powers or or
six forces that support moving through
the 11 levels nine levels sorry
they there are six powers that you're
using
forces you get to the first of the nine
levels through the power OFA means
formal education in how to meditate
right uh hearing from your Lama the
instructions for how to meditate so that
the the force that you use to get to
level number one is just education
spiritual education in how to meditate
okay
uh you reach the second level of
meditation which is what keeping the
object in the mind with some continuity
some brief continuity that's achieved
through Samba Samba means careful
consideration of what you heard in class
going home and thinking about what you
learned in class that's the second of
the six traditional
Powers you get to keeping the mind on
the object with patches where you lose
the object object and you get to
maintaining the Mind tightly on the
object through the power of your ability
to hold the object right it's called we
calling it
awareness the levels called controlling
the mind and quiring the mind are
accomplished through the power of your
Watchdog mind your
watchfulness the seventh and eighth
levels are accomplished through the
power of making some
effort applying some
effort and then level number nine is
accomplished only by what do you call
it habituation or familiarity with what
you were doing at level eight getting
used to level eight takes you to love
mind
I talked uh in detail these are just
summaries of what I already taught you
in detail
[Music]
yesterday then there are four sorts of
modes in which the Mind goes through
these levels right these are the these
are called the four modes of the Mind
uh in the the first two of the nine
levels they are accomplished through
some kind of uh purposeful concentration
of the
mud it feels like purposeful
concentration of the
mud level three to level seven right
three four five six seven five
intermediate stages from 3 to seven
including
seven they feel like you're flowing but
within interruptions they feel like flow
but with
interruptions like you keep getting
phone calls when you're trying to talk
somebody or something like
that which is what do you call it's
Stabila right it's it's exhausting
you're trying to concentrate on
someone's interrupting that's the level
three to level seven is unpleasant in
that sense your your meditation is
somebody's constantly what do you call
it
tapping you on the shoulder and getting
you drowsy or getting you
distracted at the eighth
level you are making some effort to be
there but there's nobody interrupting
you okay it's a flow without
interruption but with
effort the gupa is a flow without
interruption which is spontaneous and
has no interruption all right got
it this is a joke
okay
uh what's the feeling you have from
Level 3 to
7 interrupted you're trying to
concentrate and somebody's interrupting
right why doesn't that apply to level
one and level
two there's no flow inter R okay got it
that's what he's making a joke like
level one and level two there's not
enough moments of meditation to say you
were
interrupted okay
[Music]
what is it that
characterizes the eighth meditation
level what was the feeling what did he
say
huh yeah was it oh no I'm sorry how did
he describe the first to
love what did you say the feeling
was you had to concentrate you had to F
you had to gather your
thoughts you feel like you have to
gather your thoughts like you want to
make a call an important call you have
to call British Airways today or you're
calling Argentina for an interview and
you you don't just pick up the phone you
sit there for a few minutes and you
think about what you're going to say and
like that you gather your thoughts is it
the case that from level three to level
seven you never gather your
thoughts right so the question comes why
didn't we call that Gathering your
thoughts also why did we call level
three to level seven you're trying to
concentrate and you can get
interrupt got it he's going both
ways is it the case that you don't have
any dullness and Restless at the first
two levels it's not the case but they
are defined as interruptions to a flow
of meditation and there's no flow of
meditation it's not that you don't have
them it's just that you have so little
meditation we can't say it's interrupted
by them right then the opposite is also
true it's not that you don't gather your
thoughts at levels 3 through 7even you
do as you do at levels one two but why
it's just that uh you do have a flow of
meditation in levels 3 to S and you are
Che in Che in say chicken chicken chick
it's not chicken chicken okay chicken
chicken means those of you who are
learning to b k y i
n repeated means constantly okay Che in
cheen he's always doing that chcken
chicken CH means to do right chcken
chicken he keeps doing that it's sort of
a b bother tongue chicken chick they are
interrupting interrupting chicken
chicken they are they keep bugging they
keep interrupting so we call levels 3 to
seven the feeling of them is that you
have a flow but someone keeps
interrupting and it's exhausting
the feeling at number eight is that you
are engaging in the object without with
no interruptions you have a flow with no
interruptions T Tong means you
can uh maintain the entire session
without an
[Music]
interruption and you are not you are not
interrupted by dullness and
restlessness the feeling at the level
nine is called uh
spontaneous engagement in the object
okay just spontaneous
meditation now comes an interesting
section okay what time we got I'll start
it with you and we probably won't finish
it till the evening right here begins an
interesting
section I said that level number nine
was
not sham level number nine the highest
of these nine levels is still not enough
to see empty this you have to go further
you need level 9 plus enhancements what
do you call
it what do the athletes use it they
yeah level n with steroids is sham all
right so what are the steroids what do
you have to add to level n to see
emptiness with that state of mind okay
what's missing I mean that that should
be rather disturbing right oh you know
you just took us to like five days of
these levels and now you say I get to
level nine and I still can't see
anything right the mind is still not fit
enough to see emptiness at level n what
else what what what more you want from
me what more do you want from
[Music]
me once you reach the ninth
level you are free of subtle dullness
and subtle
restlessness you can stay in a deep
state of meditation without any kind of
what do you call effort
effortlessly means for a long time
okay
means that's only an approximation of sh
it is not actual
sh it's only close to Sham but it's not
real
[Music]
sh so here's the Crux of the point right
here's the Crux of the point how do we
move from nine to real sham what what
what do we have to do what more do you
want from me he says if you want the
real
thing you got to go back to your
practice and and keep getting a greater
familiarity with it you got to keep at
level 9 stay at level 9 and and get more
and more accustomed to to level n fluent
in number nine
okay you need sh say
sh
say uh if you're in the monastery and
you want to say somebody's a real I
almost said assle
okay and you say uh like you come home
and you're really upset at them and you
don't say he's
the which means a an Eater of certain
substances
okay I saw the D Lama in tan you know
and he has this Oxford train the
transl and and the D Lama said you know
people bug you you have to be patient
you know and then they bug you again and
you have to be patient you know and they
bug you one more time you got to keep
your patience but if they bug you after
that
tell
there're which means a a poop
eater but he didn't say poop uh and then
the translator was
like and then uh and then he said you
know you can try to repeat your patience
and then you can express your
displeasure and
uh his Holiness is really really funny
interent he's a he's a got
a he's a riot interent he's a riot thank
you uh luckily he has
this so uh why did I mention
that oh yeah Shin so if a guy comes uh
if you're really upset at somebody you
just you don't just call them a bad name
you say shindu shindu means
unbelievably acts shindu means like
indescribably stupid
shind you know he's not just dumb shinda
he's like supera super dumb all right
shindu mean Jang
means get get this okay this is
difficult it's very hard to describe
shinjang okay shinjang is very difficult
to describe J means you're good at it
when R got explaining Shin the only word
he could the only way he describe it he
used to love to watch the Olympics you
know he made me sit and watch the
Olympics with him over and over you know
too many Olympics right but he would
love the
gymnasts and shinjang means that uh
what agility okay uh which results from
frequent practice not just frequent but
constant practice the agility of an
Olympic gymnast is shinan okay
but it's divided into physical and
mental it's divided into Physical
Agility and mental agility and then it's
it's also tempered by the idea of great
pleasure okay it feels really good
mentally and physically you feel high
all right you you're
extremely agile strong
practiced
uh very good at what you do extremely
good that medit right and then you get
this kind of uh pleasure it feels good
like someone who's really good at
yoga then it just you get into a pose
and you listening to Lady Ruth do yoga
is funny because she's constantly going
ah you know she gets into a really hard
pose and she's
like you know like she's having you know
really good time with the p Okay so
it's the same with meditation what will
take you from level 9 to
shamata is an intense pleasure physical
and mental in the process of
meditation and it can only come to
constant practice by definition it is a
result of constant uh devoted effort to
meditate and then you will reach high
levels of pleasure people who you know
go to a dhit class or something yoga
class and it's very difficult but there
are some people there not me who are who
are really enjoying it you know they are
they are really in a Zone you know like
they're having a really good time when
he forces them to do strange things and
that's shinan okay they they're so good
at it that the most difficult poses
become uh High highly pleasurable to
them so that's shinan and it can be
mental and it's mental and it's bodily
when you sit down to meditate physically
you feel you feel extreme pleasure in
your body your your body is tingling
your back is just automatically in a
Groove you sit down your knees lay down
your your legs can still fall asleep
okay there's still some tingling there's
still some problem but but you're just
feel extremely
pleasurable to sit on your meditation
cree and you feel light as the feather
your body feels light and extremely
strong and you just attack your
meditation that's Shin physical then
mentally you just
feel like you are really deeply
engrossed in your favorite song that's
one thing to be engrossed right it's one
thing to be enveloped in your favorite
song it's something else to feel
Blissful about that see you feel
Blissful while you're engrossed in your
fav s the concentration five minutes of
that concentration is like an hour of
sleep you know you come out and you feel
so refreshed and happy okay it's very
very pleasurable to be able to
concentrate and then when someone's
interrupting you it's almost like
someone's depriving you of sleep you see
uh it there's a resistance to the
interruption as as if you were in a deep
seep you don't want someone to inter you
see
[Music]
me and and but once your concentration
gets good the interruption doesn't hurt
you someone can you can sit there if you
have really good concentration someone
can interrupt you every five minutes and
it doesn't really affect you that's
beyond that
okay you must give to shinan you must
get to shinan what are we going to call
it I used to translate it as practiced
ease but that's kind of
corny you have to imply that it comes
from constant practice you have to imply
that it involves
agility skill and you have to imply that
it involves Bliss I don't know of a good
word meditation Bliss how
about see Mastery doesn't imply the
Bliss part
let's call this meditation I don't know
anyway there are two forms of shin okay
there are two forms of meditation
meditative BL okay I don't know what you
call S
Shin you get physical and you get mental
which do you think comes
first they say
mental he says the mental one comes
first
the the being skilled at meditation
comes to what first let's put it that
way the the skilled part comes to what
first your body or your mind your mind
okay but the Bliss Mar the Bliss part
comes first where where first then they
say your body see the skill part comes
to your mind first the Bliss part comes
to your body first all
right by becoming skilled in meditation
mentally uh that triggers a bodily
reaction then that bodily reaction
creates a mental Bliss right like it's a
threep part flow
[Music]
I'm gonna do this
uh I'm going to do this one because it's
a little Technical and we're in the mood
and then we'll stop
[Music]
okay he's describing the question that
Teddy had the other day he was
describing Teddy was describing a a
heavy feeling in the top of his head and
well how does that relate to meditation
and what you like you know and that's an
important sensation during
meditation uh because it it is an
indicator of the movement of certain PR
so so here's a rare case where outside
of Tantra he's discussing Prana
so
uh goes into a description of the
movements of Prana triggered by Deep
concentration so chronic energy inner
energy is moving to your body triggered
by Deep states of meditation
right Nan Len is an extremely difficult
word and an extremely difficult concept
uh
say extremely difficult idea okay it
refers to extremely subtle
seeds for negative states of
mind
uh
that that there are even discussions
whether Arad still have them right so
Arad someone who's reached
nirvana by you know traditionally is
defined a someone who has permanently
ended their mental fles they cannot get
angry again in their life it's not
possible they cannot get jealous of you
they cannot have desire of you it's not
possible they have reach
Nana there are discussions whether or
not they still have very very very deep
seeds for our rels
that's called n Len N means condition
means bad Len means take it okay n Len
means to take on a bad condition but it
the whole word refers to extremely
subtle and deep-seated seeds that could
cause a relapse even in a person who
reached Nana right so there's
discussions about these seeds
right and then there are Pras related to
those seeds right there are movements of
wind in the body which are related to
deep-seated extremely deep-seated
Tendencies toward negativity mental or
physical right so there are pranas which
are which relate to those seeds that
move in the
body at certain states of
meditation the Pras which are related
to deep-seated Tendencies towards any
kind of negativity are blocked by the
deep meditation deep meditation blocks
the movement of kaana that is related to
deep seated Tendencies toward negativity
okay uh a very deep states of meditation
can prevent the movement of negative
Prana in the body alog together right
even uh Tendencies deep-seated
Tendencies not what do you call manifest
negativity even deep de seated seeds
Tendencies can move on Prana but those
are blocked by high states of meditation
sh then you get that's what's happening
in Shin okay that's what he's
describing why do you feel high why do
you feel what do you call in the groove
in the what do you call in the zone this
is in the zone shinjang means in the
zone why do you suddenly feel in the
zone what's happening
he says it all goes down to your inner
body it all boils down to your inner
body the the pr which is linked to the
deepest Tendencies towards negativity in
the human being is thought right that PR
is
stop then you get this Blissful
reaction because you have been plagued
by those negative wins for your
whole lives billions of years you you
had subtle movements of thought in your
being which were disturbing and harmful
to your health and and to your life
right and then suddenly those are
block you don't have a
single movement of Prana within your
body of a negative nature anymore at all
and then you suddenly feel you
know you've been banging your head
against the wall for millions of years
and then suddenly you stop and then Shin
okay wow that feels good
Shin go he says even the top of your
skull you will get some kind of
indication upper part of your head okay
go Lea means and and this is a very
difficult subject and it takes a lot of
personal experience and you have to be
at a high level meditation could even
get it right but there some heat
collects here at the top of the
head
uh and there even physically you get
some change in your
appearan uh and then uh heat collects
here and then uh there's a feeling of
uh I don't know the other day uh you
know my boss was asking me to fix the
uh knobs on drawers on some drawers and
they had a whole set of knobs they had
bought five years ago and no one had put
them in and I found out
why uh everyone was a different night
you know every drawer was a different
screw I had to go to was that Home Depot
and buy 12 different sizes of screws to
fix it you know and then uh but then
they were very high quality uh H handles
they were knobs but they had poured lead
into the middle of them and they had
substance you know and when you open the
drawer it feels different it has some
kind of you know what I mean weight to
it so that's that's your head feels like
that the upper part of your head there's
some inner heat there are physical
reactions that happen to your head and
then it just feels like it's
encased heavy and then the scripture
says de
it's not an unpleasant heaviness it's a
kind of a pleasant concentration of
energy in the top of your head
okay and then he gives an example to
explain what it feels like in the
monastery you are always one of the main
things to do when you're bored is to
shave each other's
head okay because you constantly have to
shave your head in the monastery so you
know they don't have electric
Shavers somebody has to sit there
carefully and with a straight
razor and and and shave your head and
it's kind of like a day off it's like
going to The Beautician uh say you know
today we don't we there's no debate
today let's do trash I'll do you you do
me you know and you sit there and it's
kind of pleasant you know except in the
winter okay uh and then it feels cold
you know they put the they splash water
on your head
and they start shaving and if it's cold
outside it feels uncomfortable for some
reason they do it outside I don't know
why maybe it's less mess uh people do it
outside their meditation cell for each
other but then sometimes what the guy
will do he'll go they'll make a little
fire and the guy
will he'll heat his hands and then he'll
shave your head and he'll keep heating
his hands on the fire and then they go
qu
and you're supposed to go you know and
and then they they kind of hold their
hands on your head sometimes they take a
a stone like it looks like lava stone or
something and they heat that in the fire
and then they hold it for a while and
then they put their hands on your head
and it feels like wow you know like you
get some reaction
okay that's how it feels when the
promise changes in the upper part of
your head do concentrate that's what it
feels now
uh you will reach right after that a
point where there's a resistance right
if there's any resistance of the Mind
towards doing good things
right like somebody says let's go to I I
used to say let's go to a movie and
everybody say yeah and I'd say it's
going to be $18 and they're all like
yeah but it's Star Trek the new Star
Trek movie or what was the other thing
what was the princess Le thing Star Wars
you know we were like in New York and
and somebody said hey John Stillwell can
get everybody tickets to the opening
night of of uh the new Star Wars movie
right and everybody popped down 50 bucks
like done you know suddenly everybody
had 50
bucks and uh then we were like uh could
we have a donation for the reading you
know it's $6 everybody's
like uh
so this resistance that you have to do a
good deal right the resistance that you
have to doing something nice
see he's
describing as the subtle resistances to
doing
goodness subtle resistances to doing
goodness where you are unable to Rouse
yourself to the goodness G mea means you
are unable to g means what you do to a
an Indian Bullock when you want him to
turn you like Whack Him with a stick
right that's
how would you say that in
English Ur is too
sof prod prod is
good okay due to your subtle resistances
to doing goodness it's difficult to prod
your mind okay but at this point because
the prct which resist have have been
pacified subdued those Pros have been
shut down
then suddenly you can do anything with
your mind that you want to and that
feels great your mind is under your
complete control your mind is your
slave instead of a wild El and it feels
good it feels great you feel high oh I
could do anything okay Shin s Shin then
you you feel mentally
or you feel in control of your mind
mental
sh because of the shutting down of The
Prana which is link to subtle
negativities right another kind of Prana
arises in the body a different kind of
Prana rises in the body what is that uh
they call it
the the Le wi okay what's Le usually
mean it means a ttic retreat where you
spend one month doing month right it's
called a Lally but what is the word
literally mean it means you are fit to
do you know like if you're supposed to
uh uh you're supposed to go play
baseball you know somebody said on
Saturday we're going to play baseball
you have to be fit you have to have a
glove you have to have the right shoes
and your body has to be you know that
you're not going to have a heart attack
running down to the first base okay so
you know you work out and you get in
shape to play a baseball game then you
are l l means you are in shape to do
that
thing L fit for
work means fit for work
[Music]
um so there are
name and there's
[Music]
okay P so a different kind of Pana
arises in your body which makes you very
uh fit strong uh clear excited
engaged right that different
l means what
L it covers the whole body it it
pervades the entire body this new p
I can do anything spreads throughout the
whole
body run means it it courses throughout
the
body then that prevents you from ever
having that negative again
yeah
uh you are happy to undertake any
virtuous thing without any what do you
call
it shumba means
uh kind of not up for it all right
without being not up
and then suddenly your body feels like a
feather they say like cotton like a wisp
of cotton in the wind your body feels
light if you do yoga well you don't have
to go crazy I mean the point is not that
you can do a handstand the point is that
your body feels like a wisp of cotton
during deep meditation and then that's
the reason to do yoga right so your body
feels light strong fit and you sit down
in
Med
from this practiced feeling of the body
and lightess of the body
suddenly uh you get
a a bliss okay what do you call
it you get like jol not jols you
it's like a euphor but it's physical
okay yeah endomorphin rush in the body
okay it's not just tingle it's like a a
feeling of
uh Bliss ECA physical
Bliss near orgasm okay all right it
feels
like really uh light strong and turned
on the
[Music]
body from that you get
mental okay where it feels like you are
sinking into the object so that's the
first time he's mentioned
that that feeling somebody mentioned it
with their
teacher uh where where you're sinking
into the object you feel like you are
lost in the
object and you don't get any
other perceptions coming up in your mind
okay you're not even aware of your body
you're not even aware of your body
you're not aware of your body
anymore and it and your mind feels like
you have sunk into the object you don't
feel separate from the object
anymore and then you get this this
really happiness as opposed to physical
Bliss so first comes physical Bliss and
then comes an emotion of deep deep
happiness deep
pleasure we're almost done
okay I just don't know where to stop in
all this pleasure
[Music]
maybe we stop
there I'll go one more line then we'll
pick it up in the middle of the okay
name and then you get kind of a what do
you call
it
Paradox you call it when there's a
problem dma who said
dma that's yeah then you get sort of a
dilemma have you lost the
object yeah cuz you you sunk into the
object right uh you sink into the object
and then and then you feel like where'
the object go okay because it doesn't
feel like it's out there anymore it
feels like you're in it it feels like
you sunk into the object and then you
might get a little weird feeling at that
moment that I lost maybe I lost the
outdate but your in the object all right
okay we'll stop there NBO it's
page
360b third line okay he's about to get
the Sham you can feel it right you're
close to sh